Guide to the Collection on the Commemoration of the 200th Anniversary of George Washington's Inauguration 1989 MS 3119
New-York Historical Society
Collection on the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of George Washington's inauguration
1989
New-York Historical Society
New York City Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution
MS 3119
.6 Linear feet in 1 box
The collection holds a set of documents compiled by the New York City Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution, which, as one of its activities, organized the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of George Washington's inauguration. The contents are primarily publicity material and ephemera: press kit; event invitations, tickets, programs, brochures, and scripts; and pins and other memorabilia. There are also 5 pieces written for the Commission by historian Richard B. Bernstein that provide historical context to Washington's inauguration and the celebration of it. The collection does not hold any of the records or other internal organizational documentation concerning the Washington commemoration or of the Commission itself.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format.
Biographical / Historical
The New York City Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution was established in September 1986 by Mayor Edward Koch. Its mandate was "to remind New York's citizenry that the Constitution is a reality in our daily lives and that it works only as well as the degree to which we take seriously our responsibility to govern ourselves." The Commission sponsored various public education programs.
Among the Commission's projects was the organization and administration of the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of George Washington's inauguration. Events included re-enactment of Washington's journey from Mount Vernon and arrival at Wall Street, a symposium on the modern presidency, a flotilla, parade, fireworks, religious service, ceremony at Federal Hall, and others.
(The above note was based on publicity documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New York City Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution, August 1989.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds a set of documents compiled by the New York City Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution for donation to New-York Historical. The contents are primarily publicity material and ephemera: press kit; event invitations, tickets, programs and scripts; pins, paperweight, stationery, and other memorabilia; brochures; and historical images. The principal events represented are the arrival ceremony of the president at South Street Seaport, "The Presidency in the '90s" symposium, presidential flotilla, fireworks display, service of thanksgiving at St. Paul's Chapel, and inaugural ceremony at Federal Hall. There are also 5 pieces written for the Commission by historian Richard B. Bernstein that provide historical context to Washington's inauguration and the celebration of it. There is an item level inventory stored with the collection. The collection does not hold any of the records or other internal organizational documentation concerning the Washington commemoration or of the Commission itself.
Separated Materials
3 posters and 4 architectural plans were removed from the collection and transferred into a format-based collection in the library's Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections (PPAC). The specific items removed are noted on the item inventory with the collection.
Related Materials
In connection with the 200th anniversary in 1989, N-YHS mounted an exhibition "George Washington in New York." Records of the exhibition, including color slides of the installation, are in the N-YHS's institutional archives in the Museum Department record group (RG-20).
Press kits.; Printed ephemera.; Publicity.; Washington, George, 1732-1799 -- Inaugurations -- Centennial celebrations, etc.
- Press kit, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder A)
  Scope and Contents
  Holds schedule of events, press release, fact sheet on George Washington, historical timeline, photographs, information about the Commission, and other contextual material
- Invitations, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Tickets, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Programs, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Transcripts/Scripts, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  Holds: transcript of "The Presidency in the '90s" symposium; scripts of the "Hail to the Chief" fireworks, St. Paul's service, Federal Hall inaugural ceremony, and parade.
- Memorabilia, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  Holds buttons/pins, cards, stationery, event credentials, parking permit, Tiffany paperweight, etc.
- Works on the history of the Washington inauguration prepared for the Commission by historian Richard B. Bernstein, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  Among the five histories here is one on the 1889 centennial celebration, drawing on Clarence Bowen's 1892 memorial volume.
- Other documents, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  Holds various items including, among others, the schedule for President George W. Bush and First Lady Laura Bush, lists of guests and sponsors, issues of "Constitution" magazine, etc.
- Miscellaneous brochures & pamphlets, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  Holds, among other documents, a walking tour guide, schedules, exhibition brochure, catalogue, etc.
- Images, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  Holds one color photo of presidential descendants (1989) and several reproductions of images from 1889.